David G. Shatwell

GitHub | in LinkedIn | ⊕ davidshatwell.com | ✓ dshatwell23@gmail.com | 🖪 +51 961-944-700

Summary

I am a Peruvian electrical engineer with 4 years of research experience. In the past, I have worked in mining and healthcare companies, developing computer vision algorithms and implementing them on real hardware to solve industry-related problems. These experiences have led me to write scientific papers and filed a patent. In the future, my goal is to pursue a PhD in computer vision and have the opportunity to work on challenging problems with top researchers in the field.

EDUCATION

2015 - 2020 Universidad de Ingenieria y Tecnologia - UTEC (GPA: 16.33/20)

Bachelors degree in Electrical Engineering

Class ranking: 1st place

2008 - 2014 Santa Maria Marianistas School (GPA: 17/20)

Class ranking: top 10th

Research & Work Experience

Hochschild Mining - R&D Engineer/Junior R&D Engineer/R&D Intern

Mar 2019 - present

- Developed a computer vision algorithm for automatic mineral classification using color analysis, texture analysis and neural networks. The algorithm has an accuracy of 95% and a maximum processing time per image of 44 ms.
- Improved existing mineral classification algorithm by adding hyperspectral images to the classification pipeline, which increased accuracy to 97%.
- Designed a machine to test new classification algorithms, consisting of a conveyor belt, a line-scan color camera, a 3D profiling camera and two industrial LED bars. Developed software to synchronize the images acquired by both cameras.
- Wrote papers and patents, presented projects to the board of the company and in conferences, supervised the ore sorting research lab, created and managed budgets for the project.

Work & Health - Computer Vision Consultant

Sep 2020 - Sep 2021

- Developed an algorithm leveraging OpenPose's keypoint and segmentation models to estimate anthropometric measurements from patient images.
- Developed an algorithm to detect temperature anomalies in different regions of patients' backs, as a proxy for detecting muscle injuries, using OpenPose and fusing color and thermal sensor images.

Jicamarca Radio Observatory - R&D Intern

Jan 2019 - Mar 2019

 Developed a data transmission system to receive data from a radar and send it to a remote computer using Gigabit Ethernet. The system consisted of custom hardware components implemented on an FPGA and a program written in C running on the microprocessor.

UTEC - Teaching Assistant of Digital Circuits Lab

Mar 2018 - July 2018

 Assisted Dr. Jimmy Tarrillo in designing lab activities, supervising students and grading lab reports. The lab activities consisted on using FPGAs to implement digital circuits with increasing levels of complexity: from logic gates to finite state machines.

PROJECTS

Classification of Satellite Images based on their Type of Terrain

GitHub

- Developed a satellite image analysis algorithm based on terrain classification that is able to identify up to five classes of terrain.
- The algorithm works by classifying small regions with local color and texture using machine learning.
- After evaluating five different classification algorithms, we found that convolutional neural networks achieved the best accuracy.

2-DOF PID Control of the Angular Position of an Industrial Plant Emulator GitHub

- Compared the performance of using traditional PID and 2-DOF PID controllers on a plant with a rotary load.
- When subjected to several disturbances, the 2-DOF PID controller has lower steady state error and settling time.
- Paper presented in IEEE conference.

AWARDS & ACHIEVEMENTS

UTEC First Class Honors: Awarded to students with the highest GPA of their class on graduation.

UTEC Undergraduate Thesis Honors: Achieved the highest possible grade on thesis dissertation.

UTEC Undergraduate Thesis Competition: Achieved second place on competition that seeked to reward thesis projects with the potential to be published in high-impact scientific journals.

UTEC Academic Achievement Scholarship: Granted each term to the two students with the highest GPA of the program.

GRE: Quant 169, Verbal 164

TOEFL: 115/120 (Reading 30, Listening 28, Speaking 27, Writing 30)

Preprints

- [1] D. Shatwell, V. Murray, and A. Barton, "Real-time mineral classification using color and texture analysis,"
- [2] D. Shatwell, A. Weston, and O. Ramos, "Classification of satellite images based on their terrain,"

PUBLICATIONS

[1] D. Shatwell, F. Salazar, and A. Rojas-Moreno, "2-dof pid control of the angular position of an industrial plant emulator," in 2020 IEEE XXVII International Conference on Electronics, Electrical Engineering and Computing (INTERCON), IEEE, 2020, pp. 1-4.

PATENTS

[1] A. Barton, V. Murray, and D. Shatwell, Method and system for the automatic classification of rocks according to their minerals, US patent application 17/774,492, EU patent application EP22173223.3, 2022.

Skills

Programming MATLAB, Python, C++

Technologies Linux, microcontrollers, FPGAs, 3D modelling

Languages Spanish (native), English (advanced)

Last updated: November 3, 2022